<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer vnto the Catholiques supplication, presented vnto the Kings Maiestie, for a tolleration of popish religion in England wherein is contained a confutation of their vnreasonable petitions, and slaunderous lyes against our late soueraigne Queene Elizabeth ... : together with an information vnto His Maiestie of diuers their wicked and treasonable practises, attempted in the life time of our late Queene ... : wherevnto is annexed the supplication of the papists, word for word as it was presented vnto the Kings Maiestie ... / written by Christopher Muriell the elder.</title>
            <author>Muriell, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18292.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">25198208</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 25198208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1857:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer vnto the Catholiques supplication, presented vnto the Kings Maiestie, for a tolleration of popish religion in England wherein is contained a confutation of their vnreasonable petitions, and slaunderous lyes against our late soueraigne Queene Elizabeth ... : together with an information vnto His Maiestie of diuers their wicked and treasonable practises, attempted in the life time of our late Queene ... : wherevnto is annexed the supplication of the papists, word for word as it was presented vnto the Kings Maiestie ... / written by Christopher Muriell the elder.</title>
                  <author>Muriell, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newlie corrected and augmented.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R.R. for Francis Burton, and are to be solde in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the White-Lyon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-D⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611. --  Catholikes supplication unto the Kings Maiestie.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER VNTO THE CATHOLIQVES S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLICATION, PRESENTED VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings Maieſtie, for a tolleration of Popiſh religion in England. WHEREIN IS CONTAINED A confutation of their vnreaſonable petitions, and ſlaunderous lyes againſt our late Soueraigne Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe happy and gratious gouernement, the Papiſts in their ſaid Supplication doe ſo peremptorilie traduce. Together with an information vnto his Maieſtie of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers their wicked and treaſonable practiſes, attempted in the life time of our late Queene his worthy predeceſſor, whoſe life they alwayes ſought meanes to extinguiſh. Wherevnto is annexed the Supplication of the Papiſts, word for word as it was preſented vnto the Kings Maieſtie: With ſome neceſſarie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations thereupon. Newlie corrected and augmented.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Chriſtopher Muriell</hi> the elder.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>R. R.</hi> for <hi>Francis Burton,</hi> and are to be ſolde in Paules Church-yard at the figne of the White-Lyon.
1603.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST GRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious renowmed Chriſtian King; IAMES by the grace of God, of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the true Catholique and Apoſtolique faith: All diuine, and celeſtiall graces, mercies, and bleſſings, be multiplyed from generation to generation, for euermore: Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Gratious, and renowmed Chriſtian King, whereas the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, (who vſurpe the name of Catholiques) hauing poſted vnto your Maieſtie, to exhibite vnto your royall perſon a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication full of vntrueths: I one of the meaneſt of your Maieſties moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loyall ſubiects, mooued with zeale of the holy and vndoubted true religion, now profeſſed in <hi>England;</hi> haue thought it not inconuenient (with your Graces fauour, which I humbly craue) to anſwer the chiefe and moſt materiall points of<pb facs="tcp:27879:3"/>the ſaide ſupplication, becauſe it tendeth to the greeuous ſlaunder of our late deceaſed Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Queene
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and alſo of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and worſhipfull perſonages of this your Graces Realme of <hi>England:</hi> and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I heare that ſome fauorites of the Romane religion, doe ſo highly extoll and aduance the learned and eloquent penning of the ſame, and the imaginary validity and force thereof, that they vaunt that it cannot be contradicted, yet doubt I not but that the plaine verity of this ſhort aunſwer will be of ſufficient force to daunt their expectations, and to bewray their vntruthes, to their deſerued diſcredit. The ſaide Supplication conſiſteth of feauen ſeuerall partes, as by peruſall thereof may appeare.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt part is their <hi>exordium,</hi> wherein they pretend <hi>faith and dutifull obedience, and loyaltie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maieſtie,</hi> the which proteſtation I pray God they may effect in verity, in as effectuall and ample manner as they haue in flouriſhing and gloſing ſhew of words profeſſed the ſame. But I commit that to God who ſearcheth the harts and reynes, time trieth all things: <hi>nil fictum diuturnum eſſepotest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In the ſecond part they doe complaine that they were
<hi>ouer-whelmed with greeuom perſecutions, by the ſeuerity of our late deceaſed Queene:</hi> We doe not a little maruell that they bluſhed not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your Grace with ſo manifeſt vntruthes,<pb facs="tcp:27879:3"/>if they ſuppoſed (as they in wordes pretend) <hi>that God hath bleſſed you with a wiſe and vnderſtanding hart, rightly to diſcerne betweene truth and faſhood:</hi> For I dare boldly affirme that they cannot prooue that any one receiued the ſentence of death onely for profeſſing the Romiſh religion, except treaſon were thereunto alſo annexed: And if it may pleaſe your moſt Gracious Maieſtie to waigh in equall ballance the perſecutions (to vſe their owne wordes) they ſuffered either by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment or fining by the purſe, (wherewith verye fewe in compariſon were touched) your highneſſe ſhall vnderſtand that their owne wilfull obſtinacie, and not the Queenes Maieſties feue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie vrged the ſame; for whenſoeuer it pleaſed them to reſort to their pariſh churches vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine prayers, they had preſent releaſement both of their impriſonment, and alſo of their fines and fees: But ſeeing that their vniuſt exclamations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force me to call to freſh remembrance the moſt ſauage and brutiſh dealings of the Papiſts in Queene <hi>Maryes</hi> dayes, how they then dominered your highneſſe cannot be ignorant: how vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully did they torment vnto death the faithfull ſeruants and Saints of God, for profeſſing the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpell of our redeemer Chriſt Ieſus? Some they tormented with moſt ſharpe and long impriſonment, ſome they whipped with roddes, ſome they ſecretly murthered in priſon, but the greateſt and generall number were ſacryficed<pb facs="tcp:27879:4"/>in the fire, in which kinde of torment they ſpared none, no not any degrees of perſons, not ſo much as women great with childe, but tormented them to death, euen when the children did fall out of the mothers wombes into the fire, in the view of the Papiſts, who being paſt ſhame and grace, nothing regarded it. Yea ſuch was their raging madneſſe, that they digged vp the dead bones of thoſe two godly and learned fathers <hi>Martin Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Phagius,</hi> and burned them in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge:</hi> It is manifeſt vnto the world, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts tortured to death, as graue, as wiſe, as vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and as learned, and Catholike fathers, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> affordeth:
<note place="margin">Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> The records of theſe things are ſo manifeſt, ſo true, and ſo freſh in memorie (of many yet liuing) that they cannot bee contradicted. But to returne to our late deceaſed Queene, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Papiſts doe vniuſtly charge her, that ſhe was <hi>A grieuous perſecutor of them,</hi> their aſſertion conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of contrarieties, for after the death of her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King
<hi>Edward,</hi> they vndelayedly perſecuted her Grace: in the dayes of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> they toſſed her from priſon to priſon, threatning her with continuall death, ſo that ſhe dayly expected the Axe to ſeuer her ſacred head from her Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhoulders:
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> in his reply to the Apo. pa. 84.</note> and once a precept was giuen for the executing thereof, to the Lieutenant of the Towre, by the treacherous dealing of one of the Popes
<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardiner</hi> Biſhop of Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> minions (the bearing great ſway in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>) in ſo much that if the Lieutenant of the<pb facs="tcp:27879:4"/>Tower had not himſelfe preſently poſted vnto the Court vnto the Queene her ſiſter, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand certainly her pleaſure therein, ſhe had dyed before the Queene had beene acquainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. But in proceſſe of time, ſhe by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence beeing freed from that danger, and her ſelfe enioying the royall Crowne, Scepter, and dignitie of the Realme: did not the Pope deale with her as his predeceſſour did in former time deale with King <hi>Iohn?</hi> By his curſed Bul he curſed and excommunicated the aforeſaid King, &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the whole realme: So that for diuers yeares none were ſuffered to be Chriſtianly buried: he charged all his ſubiects that none of them ſhould releeue, helpe, or ſuccour him by any meanes, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly or indirectly, vpon paine of his curſe: ſo that the rebellion of his nobles was ſo great that of force (to procure his peace) he was conſtrained to
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Stovves</hi> Chro: in the life of K.
<hi>John.</hi> Page 255. and 256.</note> reſigne both the kingdomes of
<hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> into the Popes hands, and did take it again of the Pope by fee farme, paying one thouſand markes yearely for the fame. And euen the like he practiſed againſt our late Soueraigne Queene
<hi>Elizabeth:</hi> But the ſacred word of God had taught her ſubiects a better leſſon of fidelity, &amp; loyalty to their Prince, then to regard his vaine &amp; wicked Bull which by his
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Felton. Stovves</hi> Chro: page
129.</note> agents he cauſed to be hanged vpon the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of London his gate. After this he inſtigated a mighty Prince (who is now dead and gone) to attempt his pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible<pb facs="tcp:27879:5"/>inuation, and with his many fold forces vtterly to ſubuerte the flouriſhing ſtate of this Realme, and to extirpate (if it had beene poſſible) the true worſhip of God. Moreouer alſo the Pope inſtigated <hi>Parry, Babington,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Lopez,</hi> and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their confederates to conſpire the Queenes vntimely death, he fent alſo his curſed brood of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites and Seminaries (the firebrands of ſedition in all kingdoms) to induce her ſubiects to rebellion: whereunto alſo the Pope (their vnholy father) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his yeerely curſe at Rome with booke, bell, &amp; candle: hereby may you plainely ſee and perceiue, that the Pope &amp; Papiſts which pretend to be (but indeed deſire rather to make) Martyrs, did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually perſecute her Maieſty and ſought all the meane that they poſſibly could to procure her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death, yet ſhame they not to cry with open mouthes vnto your Maieſty that they were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. As for our Queene, the only, omnipotent, wiſe, &amp; all ſeeing God, preſerued her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all their bloudy practiſes, &amp; gaue vnto her an happy, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, &amp; peaceable end, to his glory, her own and our comforts, &amp; to their vnſpeakable griefe &amp; ſorrow.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third part, this generation of vypers relate vnto the world their owne <hi>wicked and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous endeuors to induce ſome now liuing, to aſpire vnto the royall dignity of this kingdome.</hi> O curſed Paraſites and falſe harted Papiſts, cannot you be ſoliciters of miſchiefe, but you muſt needes brag thereof; it argueth that diſcord and rebellion are<pb facs="tcp:27879:5"/>the chiefeſt vertues (if I may ſo ſay) of your new and falſe Catholique Romiſh religion. But moſt gratious King, let vs praiſe and glorifie God, who hath ſo directed your godly proceedings by his holy ſpirit, and hath alſo giuen you wiſedom and fortitude to relie vpon his diuine prouidence, who workerh all things for the beſt, to them that ſerue and loue him. And that it hath now pleaſed God to crowne your royal head with the crowns of theſe kingdoms of <hi>England, France</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> it cannot be any wiſe imputed vnto the Papiſts, for they were (like traitors) wholy bent another waye, vntill they perceiued that their deſignes were in vaine, and their hopes fruſtrate. For no ſooner had it pleaſed God to call vnto his mercie our gracious Queene (who at &amp; before her death reſigned vnto your highneſſe, as vnto whome of right it appertained, the royal ſcepter of all her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions) but that once her, now your moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nobles, cauſed your rightfull title vnto all her kingdoms, to be by open proclamation publiſhed vnto the world, the vndoubted trueth of which your royall and lineall diſcent, together with the ſpirit of God working in their hearts to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame, hath ſo vnited the harts and minds of all the nobilitie, clergy, and communalty of this land, that all (the Papiſts excepted) doe ioye to behold your royall face, and are ready to ſerue, honour, and obaye you, with their bodies and goods euen vnto death: The Lorde bleſſe and<pb facs="tcp:27879:6"/>preſerue you from the practiſes and conſpiracies of the wicked Romaniſts (for ſurely they hate you in their harts becauſe you profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt as your predeceſſor Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did) who if (notwithſtanding their flouriſhing ſhew of words) their wicked and deſired expectations had bin effected, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the general inuaſion of this land was intended (your Maieſty knoweth by whom) neuer had your Grace inioyed the ſcepter of theſe kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> yes hardly (if they could haue effected the contrary) ſhould you haue reteyned the kingdom of
<hi>Scotland,</hi> which then (&amp; now alſo God be thanked)you poſſeſſe quietly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the fourth part they do <hi>greeuouſly complaine of two euils that doe vex their harts: The firſt is, that this Realme of</hi> England <hi>is deuided into fourereligions, to wit, Proteſtants, Papiſts, Puritans, &amp; Athiſts, ouer all which the Proteſtants did domineere all the raigne of our late diſceaſed Queene:</hi> Thus much we do truely, to the glory of God confeſſe, that all ſuch as did profeſſe the ſacred Scriptures, were protected firſt and principally by God, next by her Maieſty as an inſtrument from God, againſt the tyranny of the Pope, and all bloud-thirſty Papiſts; and that the Barrowiſtes (who may moſt iuſtly of all other among vs be termed Puritanes) as Ieſuites which are the Popiſh Puritanes amongſt them, and all Phariſaicall Iuſticiares, together with all turbulent Athieſt, (if any ſuch be) which haue ſprong vp in this flouriſhing time of the Goſpell as euill weeds<pb facs="tcp:27879:6"/>amongſt good Corne, haue beene continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by the preaching of the Goſpell, by the wiſe, aduiſed and faithfull miniſters and diſpenſers thereof in this kingdome. And we are fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the ſaid religion is ſo firmely eſtabliſhed and founded vpon the ſacred Scriptures, yea euen vpon Chriſt Ieſus that ſure rocke, and is ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie defended with the two-edged ſworde that proceedeth from the mouth of God, which is able to caſt downe ſtrong holdes, and euery high thing that ſhall exalt it ſelfe againſt God and his true Church: that the gates of hell (that is to ſay, the Diuell himſelfe, nor curſed Pope, Turke, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retique, Infidel, Papiſt or Athieſt) ſhall neuer be able to preuaile there-againſt ſo long as the world endureth. The ſecond thing they complaine of is, that <hi>warres and bloudſhed haue ſeldome ceaſed, Taskes and Subſidies neuer ſo many, diſcontented mindes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable</hi> Behold the children of the Diuell can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but lye, for their father the Diuell hath beene a lyar from the beginning: How iniuriouſly doe they charge that bleſſed buried corpes whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite is inglory, with theſe vntruths? did not euery man ſit vnder his owne Vine, and eate the labours of his hands quietly and peaceably without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation, fortie and foure yeares and better to the great admiration of the worlde?
<note n="*" place="margin">See the Kings own teſtimony of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty in the latter end of the preface prefixed before the booke of inſtructions to his ſonne. The words are theſe. But notwithſtanding ſince there is a lawfull Queene there preſently raigning, who hath ſo long, with ſo great wiſedome and felicity gouerned her kingdoms, as (I muſt in true ſincenty confeſſe) the like hath not bin red nor hard of either in our time, or ſince the dayes of the Romane Emperor
<hi>Auguſtus,</hi> &amp;c.</note> If it pleaſe<pb facs="tcp:27879:7"/>your gratious Maieſtie to peruſe the Chroncicles, you ſhall finde, that no King nor Queene before her time hath euer gouerned this realme in ſo godly peace and Chriſtian vnity, ſo long time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting it moſt: miraculouſly againſt the tyrrannie of the Pope, and all other forraine and domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call enemies. Moreouer, her Maieſtie hath beene a nouriſhing mother, and a louing Neighbour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers Princes, countries and ſtates about her (as their conſciences can witneſſe) and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude cannot but acknowledge, if not requite, and gratiouſly protected ſhe the diſtreſſed people from the bloudy tyrannie of their implacable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent, and cruel enemies. Yet hath ſhe reſigned her Kingdomes vnto your Gratious Maieſtie in ſuch ſtate as your owne eyes doe now and long may behold, and the world doth admire. And no doubt, but as the Proteſtants haue beene faithfull vnto her, ſo will they alſo be vnto your Maieſtie: wherefore let all faithfull Chriſtians, extoll, praiſe and magnifie, the omnipotent and onely wiſe God, who hath waged his battels by hir hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (in the reſpect of her ſex) a poore Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (in mans iudgement) againſt all the enemies of his ſacred Church, as he waged battell againſt
<hi>Pharao</hi> and all his hoaſt, with an armie of Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers: And therefore let the Papiſts ceaſe to publiſh ſo great vntrueth, redounding vnto their owne perpetuall ſhame and diſcredit for euer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the fift part, they make their humble ſute
<pb facs="tcp:27879:7"/>vnto your Grace, that they may obtaine <hi>freedom to vſe the Romiſh religion freely without moleſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though not openly, yet ſecretly, alledging two reaſons: the firſt is, that becauſe they be reſtrained of that liberty, your kingdomes is abhorred of all kingdomes that profeſſe the Romiſh Religion.</hi> The ſecond reaſon is, that it would bee <hi>a ioyfull thing to all the ſaid Kingdomes, to graunt them their ſaid ſutes.</hi> And to the end to induce your Grace to graunt their requeſts, they alledge two arguments. The firſt is, <hi>that the now French King yeelding to the Papiſts to ſecure the vſe of the Romiſh religion, they honored him with theſe vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable titles, Pater patriae, et pacis reſtitutor.</hi> If it be true that he now deſerueth theſe honorable titles, why then ſince that time hath not that honorable King been freed from the dangerous conſpiracie of the Papiſts, who haue diuers times ſince ſought to murder him? If it pleaſe your renowmed Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to peruſe the trecheries of the Papiſts, you ſhall find that they haue greater murdering harts then curſed <hi>Caine,</hi> who murdered his own brother. For to omitte the many and continuall treaſons and conſpiracies of the Papiſts againſt our diſceaſed Queene, did not a graceleſſe Monke poiſon King <hi>Iohn?</hi> did not a curſed Friar of <hi>France</hi> murder with a poyſoned Pen-knife the laſt diſeaſed French King?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In vita Pii quintí.</hi>
               </note> did not the Biſhops, Monkes, Friars &amp; Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites of <hi>Spaine,</hi> cauſe the kings eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Spaine</hi> to be murdered, in letting him blood? did not the Papiſts of <hi>France</hi> vrge the King of
<hi>France</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<pb facs="tcp:27879:8"/>a tragicall Butcherly maſſacre at
<hi>Paris,</hi> in poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Queene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and in a brutiſh but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherly order to murder the moſt part of the peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Nobilitie in <hi>France,</hi> their wiues and children, with a great number of the common people in diuerſe parts of his realme: So that in one yeare by one meanes and others, they did maſſacre a hundred thouſand, as by their owne hiſtories it doth appeare. But why ſhould I ſtay vpon recitall of particularities? doth not the bloudy Inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this day teſtifie, that this tyrannie is ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in <hi>Spaine,</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and amongſt other their confederates? Beholde the fruites of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Romiſh Religion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument is drawne <hi>from the graue and wiſe counſell of</hi> Salomons <hi>Counſellors vnto</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boham (<hi>ſi loquaris eis bona verba, &amp;c.</hi>) This Text is as rightly alledged, as the deuill alledged the Scripture vnto our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, when he tempted him: for there was no requeſt made vn. to <hi>Roboham</hi> as concerning religion, but onely for a mitigation of greeuous exactions. And the Counſell of <hi>Salomons</hi> counſellors in that behalfe, was both wiſe, right, and good.</p>
            <p>But in cauſes of religion, O moſt renowmed King, let the ſacred Scriptures be your direction, and preferre them before and aboue all worldly policies, royalties, dignities, and honours whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer: for therein conſiſteth your true honor, your true wiſedome, your true authoritie, and royall<pb facs="tcp:27879:8"/>dignitie. <hi>Moſes</hi> teacheth from the mouth of God,
<note place="margin">Deutero: the 15. chapter &amp; 6. verſe.</note> that if thy brother the ſonne of thy mother, or thy owne ſonne, or the daughter of thy wife that lyeth in thy boſome, or thy friend that is as thy ſoule, ſhall intiſe thee ſecretly, ſaying, <hi>Let vs goe ſerue other gods:</hi> thou ſhalt not conſent to him, nor heare him, neither ſhall thy eye pittie him, nor ſhew mercie, nor keepe him ſecret: but thou ſhalt kill him, thy hand ſhall be firſt vpon him to put him to death. And our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt hath aſſured vs, that if we confeſſe him before men, he will confeſſe vs before his heauenly Father. And if we denie him before men, he will denie vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his heauenly father. And whoſoeuer loueth Father or Mother, brother or ſiſter, wife or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or any worldly honour, riches, dignitie, or regalitie, more then him, is not worthy of him: for we cannot ſerue two Maiſters, for we ſhall ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loue the one and hate the other, or els we ſhall hate the one and loue the other. And to this effect ſerueth the perſwaſion of
<hi>Eliha</hi> vnto the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, If God be God, ſerue him, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore let the feare of God and his ſacred word, be your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; Let it be a Lanthorne to your feete, and a light vnto your pathes, that God may bee with you and bleſſe you in all your actions. And then (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>If God bee on your ſide, who can be againſt you?</hi> But if God be againſt you, who can bee with you? For moſt gracious King, if all the Kings and Potentates in the world<pb facs="tcp:27879:9"/>did loue, fauour, and honour you, what is it to the purpoſe if God be againſt you? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord bleſſe you with his grace and holy ſpirite, that no wordly thing may ſeperate you from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſu our Lord, Amen.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the ſixt part they imploy their wittes to perſwade your moſt gracious Maieſty, that their <hi>religion is venerable for antiquity, conſtant for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, irreprehenſible for doctrine, inducing to all vertue and piety, maintained by the firſt Chriſtian Emperours, ſealed with the bloud of millions of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, &amp;c.</hi> We doe not a little maruell that they be not aſhamed to auouch ſo great vntruthes. But it is truely ſaid <hi>(amiſſo pudore omnis virtus ruit)</hi> for if their aſcertions were true, why hath one Pope cauſed the dead corpes of his predeceſſor to be digged out of his graue and to be diſmembred, and haue condemned him for an heretique, and all his workes for hereſie? And the next ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor hath ratified the firſt diſmembred Pope to be good and Catholique, and all his workes Catholique: wee muſt needs be here in a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth, not knowing how to iudge which is the Catholique Pope: the condemnor, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, haue not ſome Popes beene condemned and depriued by generall counſels? hath there not beene two Popes at once, and ſometimes three, and euery one hath curſed other, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated others, and fought bloudy bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles<pb facs="tcp:27879:9"/>one againſt another, to the diſturbance of all Chriſtendome, and the ſhedding of the bloud of many thouſand Chriſtians? And he that was the valianteſt tyrant, was the moſt religious Pope. But to let them paſſe; let vs remember
<hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the Emperour, who firſt endowed the Pope with ſtately reuenewes: But in his dayes where was their holy Bread, and holy Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? where were their pardons of free remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes, both veniall and deadly? (ſoulde now for money throughout Chriſtendome to redeeme ſoules out of purgatory) where was their Ladies Chappell, their Ladyes Maſſes, their pilgrimages to Saint <hi>Iames</hi> of Compoſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, &amp;c? Where was their praying to Saintes? Where was their diabollicall authority to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue Kings and Emperours of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and to diſpoſe of them at their free will and pleaſure? Where was the ſupremacie of the Pope vniuerſally ouer all Realmes, Kings, and Emperours, and ouer all degrees of perſons ſpirituall and temporall? but it hath beene ſince great honour for an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to leade the Popes horſe by the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and for a King to hould his ſtirrope, yea for an Emperour to be a foote-ſtoole to the Pope to treade on when hee went vpon his horſe: This Luciferian pride was not heard off in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, nor long ſince: and as for the religion that was profeſſed in thoſe dayes and
<pb facs="tcp:27879:10"/>long before <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, it was the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that we in England doe now profeſſe. And it is for certaine that the Heatheniſh and Infidell Emperours, both long before
<hi>Conſtantines</hi> dayes, and long ſince, did perſecute the now profeſſed religion in England, and that it was ſealed with the bloud of many Martyrs, adorned with the vertues of many thouſand confeſſors, beautified with the bloud of the pure and Immaculate vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins: neither were the Biſhops of Rome in thoſe dayes, freed from the ſaid perſecutions. But when Infidell Emperours by Gods diuine prouidence ceaſed their tyranny; Then the Luciferian Popes by degrees and ſteps climing the higheſt ſtaffe of the ladder of pride, did ſo farre exceed in haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of hart, inſolencie, and tyranny, that they firſt did ſhake off the lawfull authoritie of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the electing and admitting the Pope, and then preſently after, they did domineere and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranniſe ouer Emperours, Kings, and all degrees of perſons ſpirituall and temporall, ſo that it is to be doubted whether the heatheniſh Emperours in their time, or the irreligious Popes in their time haue perſecuted and tormented to death the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of faithfull Chriſtians and the Saints of God. It is ſuperfluous to rehearſe the ſtories of theſe things, ſeeing they be recorded in all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtories, and in the Chronicles of all kingdomes: And wee are perſwaded that your grace hath both ſeene and read the Hiſtorie of<pb facs="tcp:27879:10"/>theſe bloudy tragedies: But of late time the Pope hath beene well plumed tof his borrowed fethers, and his Luciferian pride ſomewhat depreſſed: Yet, if the Papiſts will ſo be content, we will ioyne with them to procure that a Generall and free Counſell may be held in Chriſtendome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto both Papiſts and Proteſtantes may freelie repaire, that thereby the Church of Chriſt may haue peace, and the ignorant may be confirmed in the true faith: and to this purpoſe hath one of our learned Diuines offered himſelfe to diſpute with any Papiſts whoſoeuer (and many other will doe the like) ſo that his perſon may be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red red from perrill.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D: Sutcliffe</hi> in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to <hi>The vvoord.</hi> pag. 43.</note> This I pray God that it may be effected, and that he that is the true God may be worſhipped of all, and that <hi>Baall</hi> may be vtterly forgotten, that all Chriſtian kingdomes agreeing in true doctrine and ſinceere truth may ioyntlie acknowledge one veritie, one faith, one baptiſme, one religion, and one onely God in Trinity, and Trinitie in Vnity, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, Amen.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In the ſeuenth and laſt part they make a ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne profeſſion before God and his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, of <hi>as loyall, as obedient, and immaculate allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to your Grace, at euer did faithfull ſubiects in</hi> Scotland <hi>or</hi> England <hi>vnto your progenitors, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſincerely and truely with goods and liues to ſerue your Grace,</hi> for confirmation wherof they confeſſe <hi>merite in obeying, and demerite in diſobeying, and<pb facs="tcp:27879:11"/>therfore cannot but in ſoule be greeuouſly tormented for the leaſt preuarication:</hi> This proteſtation is indeed with a flouriſhing ſhew of good words, let the fruites of their obediences trie the veritie thereof: where was the fruites of their obediences in the dayes of their annointed Queene now deceaſed that they may haue merite for it? Theſe Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts haue ſugered wordes, but their harts be full of deadly poyſon, for although they be a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vypers, yet they can change their ſhape into an Angel of light, to deceiue the very elect, if it were poſſible. The world ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teſtifie that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifoulde treaſons and conſpiracies of the Papiſts, were ſufficient teſtimonies of their demerit: And if they muſt needes be <hi>tormented in ſoule and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for their leaſt preuarication,</hi> needs muſt thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of their ſoules and conſciences be tormented for their many treaſons &amp; conſpiracies, againſt their late annointed Queene now deceaſed. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they profeſſe in wordes, it is impoſſible ſo long as they profeſſe the Romiſh religion to bee faithful ſubiects vnto your grace, for this is a max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime in the minds of moſt papiſts, <hi>fides non eſt ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da cum hereticis,</hi> &amp; we are ſure that the Pope hath cenſured al Proteſtant Princes for heretickes, and their religion for hereſie: Therefore whatſoeuer they profeſſe in wordes, they cannot ſerue God and the deuill, neither can they truely ſerue and obaye you and the Pope: (Two ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties cannot concur in one ſubiect) And thus<pb facs="tcp:27879:11"/>I conclude, praying to God (as our bounden du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie requireth) that of his great goodneſſe, he will vouchſafe to bleſſe, preſerue, and defend your royall maieſtie, our noble Queene, and all your Princely Children, from all your enemies both forraine and domeſticall, ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and from the treaſons and conſpiracies of all Romaniſts: That your ſacred Maieſtie and your poſterity, may liue and raigne ouer vs in the feare of God, and to his honour and glory, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall dignity, happy proſperitie, godly peace and vnity, and that after this life, you may haue celeſtiall felicitie in the life to come for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt humble and dutifull ſubiect</hi> CHRISTOPHER MVRIEL, <hi>Senior.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="supplication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:12"/>
            <head>THE CATHOLIKES SVPPLICATION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most puiſſant Prince, and orient Monarch,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch are the rare perfections and admirable gifts of wiſedome, prudence, valour and iuſtice, wherewith the bountifull hand of Gods diuine Maieſtie hath endued your Maieſtie, as in the depth of your prouident iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we doubt not but you foreſee what concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth both the ſpirituall and temporall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all your kingdoms &amp; dominions.
2. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding your Graces moſt afflicted ſubiects and
<note n="a" place="margin">I pray God that your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie neuer ſtand in neede of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> deuoted ſeruants, the Catholikes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, partly to preuent ſiniſter informations, which happily may poſſeſſe your ſacred eares, before our anſwere bee heard; partly almoſt as men ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with
<note n="b" place="margin">If they be perſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are the cauſe thereof, for they are neuer well but when their heads are hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of rebellion.</note> perſecutions for our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we are enforced to haue ſpeedie recourſe, in hope of preſent redreſſe from your Highneſſe, and to preſent theſe humblelines vnto your royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to pleade for vs ſome
<note n="c" place="margin">As you deſerue, ſo I pray God you may haue.</note> commiſeration and<pb facs="tcp:27879:13"/>fauour. 3. What
<note n="d" place="margin">Nay, what deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and vnnaturall deſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will they not, to their power, at the Popes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? for they hold it a matter of great merit at the Popes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to kill and murder their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. See <hi>Parry</hi> his Treaſons, <hi>Squire</hi> his treaſons: Likewiſe <hi>Peter Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricre,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell,</hi> their deſperate attemptes againſts the <hi>French</hi> King, Ieſuites Catechiſme 3. booke, page
148. 155.</note> allegeance or dutie can any temporall Prince deſire or exped at his vaſſalls hands, which we are not addreſſed to performe? How many Noble-men and worthy Gentlemen, moſt zealous in the Catholike Religion, haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſome loſſe of lands and liuings, ſome exile, others impriſonment, ſome the effuſion of bloud &amp; life for the
<note n="e" place="margin">Buſie fellowes, that would take in hand ſuch treaſonable actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had acquainted the partie for whom they vndertooke them therewith. Ieſuites Catechiſme 3. booke, page
138.</note> aduancement of your bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers right vnto the ſcepter of <hi>Albion?</hi> Nay, whoſe ſinger did euer ake, but Catholikes, for your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties preſent title &amp; dominions? How many
<note n="f" place="margin">Happie is that countrie, that is rid of them, for it is better haue their roome then their compaine.</note> fled to your Court offering themſelues as hoſtages for their friends, to liue &amp; die in your Graces
<note n="g" place="margin">His Maieſtie in publique Print acknowledgeth (and euer did) that Queene <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> was lawfull Queene, and therefore muſt thoſe that ſo offered themſelues, by the Kings owne teſtumonie be traytors.</note> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, if euer Aduerſary had oppoſed himſelf againſt the equitie of your cauſe? If this they attempted with their Princes diſgrace, to obtaine your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties grace; what will they do? nay, what wil they not doe, to liue without diſgrace in your Graces fauour? 4. The maine of this Realme, if we reſpect Religion (ſetting petty ſects aſide) conſiſteth vpon foure parts: Proteſtants, who haue dominiered all the former Queenes dayes: Puritanes, who haue crept vp apace among them: Atheiſts or Polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, who were bred vpon their brawles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions<pb facs="tcp:27879:13"/>in matters of faith: And Catholikes, who as they are oppoſite to all, ſo are they deteſted of all, becauſe Errour was euer an enemie to Truth. Hardly all, or any of the
<note n="h" place="margin">No thankes to them, for if their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes could haue beene ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, all proteſtants throates had beene cut long agone: call to minde they yeare 1588, and then iudge whether it be ſo or not.</note> firſt, two, three can be ſuppreſſed: and therefore we beſeech your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to yeeld vs as much fauour, as others of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie religion (to that which ſhall he publikely profeſſed in England) ſhall obtaine at your hands. For if our fault be like, or leſſe, or none at all; in
<note n="i" place="margin">They pleade m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, if they may not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted freely to vſe their Idolatrous religion.</note> equitie, our puniſhment ought to bee like, or leſſe, or none at all. The Gates, Arches, and Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mides of France proclaimed the preſent King <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter patriae &amp; pacis reſtitutor,</hi> becauſe that kingdome being well nigh torne in pieces with ciuil warres, and made a pray to forraine foes, was by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident wiſe dome and valour acquired in it ſelfe, and hoſtile ſtrangers expelled; the which he prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally effected by condeſcending to
<note n="k" place="margin">Hath he beene ſince that time freed from the danger of Papiſts, ſearch the <hi>French</hi> Chronicles, and you ſhall finde the contrarie.</note> tollerate them of an aduerſe religion, to that was openly profeſſed. Queſtionleſſe, dread Soueraigne, the kingdome of England, by cruell perſecution of Catholikes, hath bin almoſt odious to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Nations: Trade and traffique is decayed, wars and bloud hath ſeldome ceaſed, Subſidies and taxes neuer ſo many,
<note n="l" place="margin">None (or very few) diſcontented but Papiſts, whoſe heads do alwayes ake but when they are working of treaſons, and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of others into the ſame ſtate of diſcontentment with them.</note> diſcontented minds innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable; all which your Maieſties princely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuencie to your humble Suppliants, the afflicted<pb facs="tcp:27879:14"/>Catholikes, will eaſily redreſſe, eſpecially at your Highneſſe ingreſſe. <hi>Si loquaris ad eos verba lenia, erunt tibi ſerui cunctis diebus,</hi> ſaid the ſage Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of
<hi>Salomon</hi> to <hi>Rehoboham.</hi> For enlargement af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affliction reſembleth a pleaſant gale after a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement
<note n="m" place="margin">The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts haue cauſed more ſtormes &amp; tempeſts to ariſe in this land, then all other Sects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that they can inuent names for. Who but Papiſtes ſought meanes induce the late Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> (if he would haue beene atraytour to his Prince) to be a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioner for the King of <hi>Spaine?</hi> Earle of
<hi>Eſſex</hi> his owne Apologie. Yet had they vnder-hand acquainted therewith the late Lord Treaſurer Sir <hi>VVilliam Cecill,</hi> inſomuch that if the Earle had conſented vnto them, preſently had he beene entrapped. <hi>VVatſon</hi> the Prieſtin his booke of <hi>Quod libetts.</hi>
               </note> tempeſt: and a benefit in diſtreſſe dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the value thereof. 5. How gratefull will it be to all Catholike Princes abroad, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your Maieſty, to vnderſtand how Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">A manifeſt ſlander of his Maieſtie, for ſhe was farre more merciful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them then euer they deſerued. Nay the Prieſts themſelues in their own bookes acknowledge the iuſtice of his Maieſties lawes againſt them</note> ſeuerity is changed into your royall clemencie: and that the lenitie of a man reedified that which the miſinformed anger of a woman deſtroyed: That the Lion rampant is paſſant, whereas the paſſant had beene rampant? How acceptable ſhall all your ſubiects be to all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like countries, who are now almoſt abhorred of all, when they ſhall perceiue your Highneſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared not and pikes and priſons for the profeſſours of their faith, but permitted them Temples and
<note n="o" place="margin">To offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vpon vnto their Popiſh Idols</note> Altars for the vſe of their Religion? Then ſhall we ſee with our eyes, and touch with our fingers that happy benediction or
<hi>Eſay</hi> in this land, that ſwords are changed into ploughs, and launces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſithes. And all Nations admiring vs will ſay, <hi>Hi ſunt ſemen cui benedixit Dominus.</hi> Wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt no more fauour at your Graces hands, then<pb facs="tcp:27879:14"/>that wee may ſecurely profeſſe that Catholike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which al your happy Predeceſſours profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, from
<hi>Donaldus</hi> the firſt conuerted, vnto your Maieſties peereleſſe Mother laſt martyred. 6. A Religion venerable for
<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi> in his challenge vnto <hi>N.D.</hi> hath proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the contrary, chap. the 2. page 27.</note> antiquity, maieſticall for amplitude, conſtant for continuance, irreprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for doctrine, inducing to all kinde of vertue and piety, diſſwading from all ſinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. A Religion beloued by all primitiue Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, eſtabliſhed by all Occumenicall Councels, vpheld by all ancient Doctors, maintained by the firſt and moſt Chriſtian Emperours, recorded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt alone in all Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, ſealed with the bloud of millions of Martyrs, adorned with the vertues of ſo many Confeſſors, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the purity of thouſands of Virgines, ſo conformable to
<note n="q" place="margin">Therein I thinke they ſpeake more truly then they are aware of.</note> natural ſence and reafon, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſo agreeable to the ſacred text of Gods word and Goſpell. The free vſe of this Religion we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, if not in publike Churches, at leaſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes; if not with approbation, yet with toleration, without moleſtation.
7. Aſſure your Grace that howſoeuer ſome Proteſtants or Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, incited by morall honeſty of life, or innated inſtinct of nature, or for feare of ſome temporall puniſhment, pretend obedience vnto your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe lawes; yet certainely the onely
<note n="r" place="margin">Are the chiefeſt ſtirrers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all Chriſtian common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths.</note> Catholikes for conſcience ſake obſerue them. For they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending that
<note n="ſ" place="margin">A meere vntrueth, for no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants maintaine any ſuch poſition.</note> Princes precepts and ſtatutes oblige no ſubiect vnder the penalty of ſinne, will little<pb facs="tcp:27879:15"/>care in conſcience to tranſgreſſe them which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally are tormented with the guilt of finne. But Catholikes confeſſing merite in obeying, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit in tranſgreſſing, cannot but in ſoule be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tortured, at the leaſt preuarication thereof. Wherefore moſt mercifull Soueraigne, wee your long afflicted ſubiects, in all dutifull ſubmiſſion, proteſt before the Maieſty of God and all his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, as loyall obedience, and as immaculate allegeance vnto your Grace, as euer did faithfull ſubiects in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> vnto you High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Progenitours; and intend as ſincerely with our goods and liues to
<note n="t" place="margin">As long as your Maieſtie will ſerue their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, but no longer. Let them all oh Lord, if it be thy will, be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with vs in one truth. Amen.</note> ſerue you, as euer did the loyalleſt Iſralites King <hi>Dauid,</hi> or the truſty legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Romane Emperours. And thus expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Maieſties cuſtomarie fauour and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bounty, we reſt your deuoted Suppliants to him whoſe hands do manage the harts of Kings, and with reciprocate mercie will requite the mercifull.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ſacred Maieſties moſt deuoted Seruants.</hi> The Catholikes of <hi>England.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27879:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
